Let's talk about one of the most
interesting and visually significant
moments in Matt Reeves the Batman from
2022.
This one here.
Now, there are a bunch of interesting
technical elements and decisions that
work to make this moment as striking as
it is. So, I wanted to take a closer
look at a few key shots and share what I
think makes them so cinematically
noteworthy. So, without beating around
the bush, let's get straight into it.
[music]
Thematically speaking, this scene is
about one emotion, hope. So, all the
technical and cinematographic elements
here had to work together to bring that
emotion to the forefront of the
audience's experience. [music]
The flare is the central physical
element that captures this sentiment.
And when a light source like this is
used, a source that is originating in
the film's world, it's known as diioetic
lighting. [music] And Reeves seems to
really like to push the boundaries of
diioetic lighting in his world.
But in this scene here, there are some
other really interesting diioetic light
sources for us to consider.
So, let's rewind a bit to where I
actually want to start this breakdown
from
this moment here, which to me is a
pretty interesting use of diioetic
lighting. It would have probably been
easier for the filmmakers to use a
singularly colored stage light
flickering in the dark to create this
visual texture of the light bouncing off
the water, but that probably wouldn't
have led to the same dynamism that's
created by the contrasting blue and red
of a sinking GCPD card.
It takes this from being not just a
diagetic light source, but a dynamic
light source, too. And it adds a really
nice subtle visual conflict [music]
between the cold blue and the warm red.
and in doing so creates an immediately
more interesting shot.
>> Maybe this choice was influenced by
color theory, but considering the
instinctive [music] approach Reeves took
to the color palette of this film.
>> There were certain colors that we
started drawing into our palette and
they were always there and we would just
look at we were shooting and Greg would
sometime he could dial it in and he
could say, "Is this is this right for
this scene?" And there were some places
where
>> I would argue that this is just an
example of when it's more about making a
shot more striking than symbolic.
>> Still, maybe there is actually some
symbolic intention behind the use of the
sinking GCPD car to show that finally
Batman's vigilante status is changing
for the better.
I'll let you decide that. In the
meantime, there's a little bit more to
the use of the dynamic light source here
that I find quite interesting from a
technical perspective. [music]
It gradually peters out and ultimately
fails, which seems to me like a really
effective way of gently moving the
audience from the previous and very
chaotically lit sequence into the
calmer, singularly colored atmosphere
that's about to be thrust upon us. Not
only would it be a much bumpier, more
sudden visual transition if it just
suddenly went black when Batman hits the
water.
But it's also a really nice example of
how Greg Fraser and the film's lead
colorist, David Cole, use lighting and
color to subliminally cue the [music]
audience into certain emotional
responses. This failing flickering light
followed by a moment of total darkness
makes this one
feel much more impactful.
And now we're back here where I want to
draw your attention [music] to the
blocking because even though the
slightly high angled extreme wide shot
that Greg Fraser gives us is the perfect
way to frame flare wielding Batman
amidst the [music] chaos whilst helping
us get a better grasp of the scene's
geography. This shot choice really just
appears to be a vehicle for some greater
and more subtle visual storytelling.
Reeves and Fraser make very artistic
[music] use of the Yaxis in their
approach to blocking here with Batman
moving more vertically through the frame
as he waves [music] towards the collapse
scaffolding centered here at the top of
the frame. Taken together with how
Batman is generally positioned as the
tallest and most authoritative figure in
every frame from here on in, the
compositions throughout this entire
sequence [music] hit all the right
thematic notes for this moment in the
story. Through their subtle verticality,
they help visually communicate the idea
of Batman rising up in [music] the
estimations of the people of Gotham and
finally starting to achieve that good
old hero status he's most commonly
associated with. In short, these are the
shots that bring about Batman's
transformation into a hero.
And in doing so, they highlight one of
the most striking aspects of this
sequence, which is how Reeves uses all
these technical aspects, the lighting,
the blocking, the shot choices as tools
to juxtapose Batman's transition into a
symbol of hope with the uncertainty
still surrounding his image in the eyes
of the Gothamites.
Please don't hurt me.
>> Take these shots here for instance that
make use of this low angled shot from
the perspective of the survivors peering
up at the brightly lit but oddly obscure
and poorly defined figure of Batman
which is a [music] pretty nice way of
visually conveying their hesitancy to
accept this newer, more hopeful idea of
the Batman. It isn't until this little
lad reaches up and is helped out of the
water that Batman's image becomes
briefly more defined against the hopeful
light of the flare, which fortunately
[music] cues a more trusting vibe in the
other survivors, at which point we pull
back to a wide shot framing everyone in
the scene together and giving us [music]
a glimpse of these guys over here
reacting very differently to Batman
compared to how they did just a few
moments prior.
And how about that thematic resonance of
it being Mitchell's son who reaches up
first, the boy who has appeared in most
of the film's major moments. Is this
symbolic of the fallout caused by
Riddler's chaos finally coming to an
end? Or is it signaling the [music]
reconciliation of Bruce's vengeful
vigilante persona with his emotionally
scarred, vulnerable orphan persona?
Maybe it's both. But either way, along
with this entire final sequence and the
subsequent epilog type sequence
mirroring the film's opening, which it
does
really nicely,
>> I'm vengeance.
>> Including Mitchell's son here serves as
a really satisfying way of bringing the
story's narrative full circle. And
speaking of satisfying, how can I not
mention this final bird's eye view shot?
A perfectly balanced composition that
just screams stability and solidarity
with everyone in the frame moving in
unison in one common direction, sharing
one common emotion as they converge on
Batman and his beacon of hope and
heroism. In most other films, such a
sentiment would be cheesy. Here though,
it's art. Now, with all that said, the
thing I want to leave you on is actually
the sound design, because this is the
first and only time in the entire film
that the world of Gotham fades away and
the film's score completely takes over.
And it's when Batman lights the flare
that this happens.
[music]
Imagine if you will what this stadium
would actually be sounding like at this
moment. People are screaming, yelling,
crying. Water is gushing in. Metal is
creaking. Objects are slamming into each
other. It's the epitome of stress which
Reeves does let us hear for a very brief
moment.
And he could have let us hear this
throughout, but this scene is about
hope. And where we have the visual cue
of Batman as the sole [music] source of
light in the darkness, it's not just the
visuals alone that make the moment here.
It's also the decision to make Michael
Jakino's score the only audible sound.
When the flare is lit, it quite
literally burns away the sound of the
mayhem.
[music]
This approach to the sound design
combined with the bright warm red of the
flare very quickly and calmly tunes us
out [music] of the chaos and creates an
aura of tranquility throughout the
scene. It's simple. It's not overly
in-your-face or pretentious. And it's
one of the many fine examples of how
Reeves, Fraser, Cole, and the sound team
blend their visual and oral storytelling
[music]
so well with the central themes of each
key moment. Greg Fraser's cinematography
here is undeniably amazing. [music] But
it's with the help of these other areas
that Reeves and the team behind The
Batman could breathe the cinematic life
into this moment of heroic
transformation and make it such a
striking and memorable example of this
film's audiovisisual storytelling.
Once again, there are so many levels to
the beauty of cinematic moments like
this and how we experience it. And
ironically, I've still only scratched
the surface here. I guess all we can do
is keep appreciating and learning from
all the interesting things these artists
and filmmakers are doing. In the
meantime, I hope you enjoyed the video
and thank you very much for watching.
[music]